Division of Invertebrate Zoology Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
- Labels, 1864-Present; Series II
  - Zooplankton Box Labels., 1864-Present; 006551
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006588
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006589
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006590
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006591
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006592
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006593
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006594
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006595
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006596
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006597
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006598
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006599
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006600
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006601
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006602
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006603
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006604
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006605
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006606
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006607
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Box separated into 2 bins. The original label has been retained with the first bin., 006608
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Box separated into 2 bins. The original label has been retained with the first bin., 006609
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Box separated into 2 bins. The original label has been retained with the first bin., 006610
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006611
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006612
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006613
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006614
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006615
    - Zooplankton Box Labels. Digital archive only. Boxes have been discarded., 006616
- Accession Related Materials, 1864-Present; Series III
  These are archives related to the Divsional accessions.
  - Alphonse P. Bel. Archives related to YPM Acc. No. 5609. A collection of shells from Alphonse P. Bel., 1944; 001042
    - Alphonse P. Bel. Catalog of shells collected by Alphonse P. Bel., 31 Oct 1944; 001043
  - Capt. James Pedersen Collection. Archives related to the Capt. James Pedersen Collection from La Paz, Mexico, Gulf of California., 1867-1870; 001211
    - Capt. James Pedersen Collection. A List fo Shells collected by Capt. Pedersen and sent to P.P. Carpenter for identification by W. Fergesson. Questionably related to YPMZ Acc. No. 443., 1867-1870; 001212
    - Capt. James Pedersen Collection. A list of numbered shells received from Capt. Pedersen. See Invoice Ledger. Questionably related to YPMZ Acc. No. 443., Apr 1869; 001394
  - Eldridge Collection. Materials related to YPMZ Acc. No. 1197., 1889; 001317
    - Eldridge Collection. List of Unios in the Eldridge collection., 1889; 001319
    - Eldridge Collection. A letter to Rev. Eldridge from W.A.[illegible] informing him he is sending a box of Cirnoidea. There is a Verrill note on the top of the letter saying "When the Eldridge collection arrived at Yale University the Crinoids had nearly all been mixed up and labels were misplaced or lost. Probably most of them were from the source named below", 26 Jan 1863; 001318
  - F.H. Bradley Subscription of 1866. Archives related to the F.H. Bradley Subscription of 1866, expedition to Central America., 1866 - 1867; 001209
    - F.H. Bradley Subscription of 1866. A shipping receipt for 4 cases of specimens shipped on 11 Aug 1866. On the reverse side, in Verrill's hand, are a listing of the expeditions lots and their localities., 1866 - 1867; 001210
  - Frank H. Bradley Subscription of 1866. Archives related to the F.H. Bradley Subscription of 1866. Collections from Central America., 1866-1867; 001451
    - Frank H. Bradley Subscription of 1866. A list of specimens from Pedro Gonzalez Island, Panama dredges. See Invoice Ledger., 1866-1867; 001452
  - George Comer Collection. Archives related to the George Comer collection, YPMZ Acc. No. 1135 & 1199., 1889; 001351
    - George Comer Collection. Measurments of eggs in the George Comer Collection. Eggs are from Gough, South Georgia and Kerguelen Islands., 1889; 001352
    - George Comer Collection. List ofbird skins from Gough and Kerguelen Islands. From G. Comer., 1889; 001355
    - George Comer Collection. A bound compilation of G. Comer observations and lists of birds related to his collection., 1889; 001356
  - IP Accession No. 7241. Archives related to IP Acc. No. 7241, Alexander Winchell Collections., 1860-1880; 001458
    - IP Accession No. 7241. A list of fossils sent to A.E. Verrill from A. Winchell, from Niagara Shale, Indiana; Hamilton Shales, Ontario; and the Hamilton Group, Michigan., 30 Aug 1866; 001459
  - IZ Accession No. 7525. Archives related to IZ accession number IZA.07525, corals, etc. from C. F. Dai, mostly used for his dissertation., 1986; 006526
    - IZ Accession No. 7525. Four photographs of corals in situ, O-Lan-Pi, Taiwan, 11 Aug 1986, 12 meters., 006527
  - IZ Accession No. 7663, U.S. Exploring Expedition. Archives related to the U.S. Exploring Expedition., 1838-1870; 001456
    - IZ Accession No. 7663, U.S. Exploring Expedition. A list of the Duplicate Shells of the U.S. Exploring Expedition., 001457
  - J. A. McNiel Expedition to Central America. Archives related to the J.A. McNiel Expedition to Central America. See IZ Acc. No. 7769., 1868-1869; 001206
    - J. A. McNiel Expedition to Central America. A list of the Crustacea of the J.A. McNiel's Expedition., 12 Oct 1869; 001207
    - J. A. McNiel Expedition to Central America. A list of the localities of the J.A. McNiel's Expedition., 1869; 001208
  - J.K. Payne Collection. Archives related to YPMZ Acc. No. 1115, a collection of freshwater shells from J.K. Payne., 1885-1886; 001223
    - J.K. Payne Collection. A letter from J.K Payne to E.S. Dana inquiring if the collection of shells he sent had arrived yet., 15 Feb 1886; 001224
  - Le Roy Collection. Materials related to the Le Roy Collection, YPM Acc. No. 2462., 1898; 001119
    - Le Roy Collection. 2 lists of boxes and their Zoological contents., 1898; 001120
  - Thomas J. Whittemore. Archives related to YPM Acc. No. 5248. A collection of shells from Thomas J. Whittemore, Curator of Conchology of the Boston Society of Natural History, inclusive dates unknown., 1797-1872; 001001
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Various catalogs and publications relating to the Thomas J. Whittemore collection., 1797-1872; 001016
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. A catalog of Publications and Mollusca in the collection., 1797-1872; 001784
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with T. Prince [? illegible frist name]., 1797-1872; 001859
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with Zadock Thompson., 1797-1872; 001860
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with John Bartlett., 1797-1872; 001861
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Notes by T.J. Whiitemore and a newspaper clipping from 12 Nov 1850 from the Boston Daily Evening Traveler on the Boston Scoiety of Natural History., 1797-1872; 001862
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Miscellaneous requests for exchanges with T.J. Whittemore. Many dated in the 1840's., 1797-1872; 001863
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with Ludwig Parreyss., 1840-1860; 001857
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Some dealing with exchanges. Some dealing with the Building Committee for the Boston Society of Natural History., 1840-1861; 001866
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Miscellaneous correspondence, notes, lists of mollusca, etc. Some dealing with exchanges, some personal business, and some dealing with the Boston Society of Natural History., 1840-1870; 001868
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Many of the Whittemore Archives were found in a box with this cover., 1840-1870; 001869
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with William Stimpson, dated in the 1850's, 1850-1860; 001864
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with Dr. James Lewis., 1850-1865; 001865
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Apparently all dealing with exchanges with John G. Anthony., 1850-1870; 001858
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. Correspondence, lists of molluscs etc. Mostly dealing with exchanges with John A. McNeil., 1859-1861; 001867
    - Thomas J. Whittemore. A catalog of shells of the Thomas J. Whittemore Collection. Includes an introduction discussing the genesis of the collection., 1864; 001002
  - WIlliam James Beal Collection. Archives related to YPMZ Acc. No. 206, the William James Beal Collection., 1866; 001201
    - William James Beal Collection. A list of freshwater Mollusca from the William James Beal Collection., 1866; 001202
  - YPM Accession No. 663. Materials related to YPM acc. No. 663, collected by W.B. Pease., 1874; 001357
    - YPM Accession No. 663. List of birds and mammals collected by W.B. Pease., 1874; 001358
  - YPM.12600. Archives related to accession YPM.12600., 1974; 006543
    - YPM.12600. Original label describing the provenance of the collection., 1974; 006544
  - Zoology Accession No. 1017. Archives related to the George Comer collection, YPMZ Acc. No. 1017., 1889; 001353
    - Zoology Accession No. 1017. List of skins presented by B. Silliman. Collected by E.F. Lorquin, San Francisco, CA., 22 Jun 1881; 001354
  - Zoology Accession No. 13. Archives related to YPMZ Acc. No. 13., 1864; 001463
    - Zoology Accession No. 13. A letter from W.A. Clapp to J.D. Dana informing him he is sending the fossils., 1864; 001464
  - Zoology Accession No. 21. Archives related to YPMZ Acc. No. 21., 1864; 001407
    - Zoology Accession No. 21. A letter from T. Bland to J.D. Dana informing him he is forwarding the shells he identified collected by C. Wright from Cuba. See Invoice Ledger., 20 Dec 1864; 001408
  - Zoology Accession No. 41. Archives related to YPMZ Acc. No. 41., 1864; 001467
    - Zoology Accession No. 41. A letter from C.M. Wheatley to J.D. Dana informing him he is forwarding the shell specimens he identified from Prof. Silliman collected in the Nevada territory. See Invoice Ledger.., 11 Nov 1864; 001468
  - Zoology Accession No. 420. Acrhives related to Zoology Accession No. 420., 1868; 001399
    - Zoology Accession No. 420. A list of Hymenopter receieved from Edward Norton. See Invoice Ledger., Dec 1868; 001400
  - Zoology Accession No. 566. Archives related to accession YPMZ No. 566., 1870; 001392
    - Zoology Accession No. 566. A letter and list of birds from India collected by George A. Kittredge., 12 Nov 1870; 001391
  - Zoology Accession No. 8. Collections of Rev. George H. Apthorp. See YPM Zoology Acc. No. 8., 1843; 001453
    - Zoology Accession No. 8. A Letter from G.H. Apthorp to Benjamin Silliman informing him he is sending collections from Sri Lanka. See Invoice Ledger., 11 Oct 1843; 001455
    - Zoology Accession No. 8. List of collections from G.H. Apthorp. Box No. 2 contained all Anthropological material. Box No.1 had corals (Worked on By J.D. Dana). See Invoice Ledger., 1843; 001454
- Divisional Indices, 1866-Present; Series IV
  Divisional indices of citations, specimens, etc.
  - Citation Indices. Indices of citations and descriptions. Appear to be used as "quick reference guides"., 1866-Present; 001038
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index of various Mollusca species. Unknown if used for a publication., 1864-1926; 001702
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index with description of various Cephalopoda species., 1864-1926; 001703
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index with description of various Gastropoda species. Also has USFC data sheets for each species mentioned., 1864-1926; 001704
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index with description of various Gastropoda species. Also has USFC data sheets for each species mentioned., 1864-1926; 001705
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index of original descriptions for various invertebrate species, appearing to be compiled by either K.J. Bush or C.E. Bush., 1866-1914; 001039
    - Citation Indicies. Citation index for various species of Achatinella. Includes synonymies and habitat. One is bound, the other is unbound. Most of the citations are pre-1860., 001785
  - Miscellaneous., 002803
    - Porifera Index Cards. A miscellaneous collection of index cards containing Porifera names, station and specimen numbers. Context unknown, presumably W.D. Hartman., 002774
- Acquisitions, Loans and Exchanges, 1864-Present; Series V
  Archives related to Divisional aquisitions, loans and exchanges. Not always related to accessions.
  - Aquisitions. Archives related to the Divisional Aquisitions., 1864-Present; 001087
    - Aquisitions. A list of bird eggs apparently sent to Yale College from the Smithsonian. See Invoice Ledger., 13 May 1869; 001388
    - Aquisitions. A list of Insects donated to the collection during 1866., 001204
    - Aquisitions. A reprint of a T.H. Bean (1880) publication. See bibliography record IZ.11632. Numerous UNSM numbers are checked off, presumably duplicates of those specimens are in the Museum., 001361
    - Aquisitions. A letter and specimen list from G.B. Goode to A.E. Verrill informing him of specimens sent to the YPM from the USNM. They include ocean bottom samples, Crinoidea, Ateroidea and collection of dupilcate deep sea fishes. The Crinoidea and fish were sent in exchange for the valuable services Verrill had rendered for the Museum. The ocean bottom samples and Asteroidea were sent for study on J.E. Benedict's recommendation. There is a list of the deep-sea fishes, received in good order by A.E. Verrill, 15 Dec 1894., 24 Nov 1894; 001115
    - Aquisitions. A letter sent to A.E. Verrill via Prof. William Beebe in regards to Lepidoptera and other Insects collected around Eagle City, Alaska by Plato Mountjoy collected from Jul 1900 to 16 Aug 1900. The letter is describing the collection, apparently sent to Verrill., 001083
    - Aquisitions. A list of Crustacea received from the Smithsonian. See Invoice Ledger., Dec 1875; 001364
    - Aquisitions. A list of bird species and lot counts. Possibly an aquisition., 001341
    - Aquisitions. A list of Hydroida from Bergen, Norway. It is in S.F. Clarke's hand., 001344
    - Aquisitions. A list of fishes received from the MCZ. See Invoice Ledger., 001362
    - Aquisitions. A list of Butterflies from Norway, ME. See Invoice Ledger., 001363
    - Aquisitions. A list of Mammals, possible received from the Smithsonian. See Invoice Ledger., 001365
    - Aquisitions. A list of invertebrates (Cephaolopoa, Echinodermata, etc.) from Thomas A Streets of the U.S. Stmr. Portsmouth. See Invoice Ledger., 001366
    - Aquistions. A list of bird eggs sent to Yale College from the Smithsonian. Printed numbers are USNM catalog numbers. See Invoice Ledger., 04 Jun 1865; 001470
    - Aquistions. A list of coral specimens given to A.E. Verrill from the Essex Institue for services in identifying their collections. See Invoice Ledger., May 1868; 001469
  - Correspondence. Correspondence relating to Divisional aquisitions, loans and exchanges., 1864-Present; 001092
    - Corresdpondence. A letter from Dr. Vaughn, McGill University, Montreal Canada, to C.E. Bush, acknowledging the receipt of specimens forwarded by her., 13 Aug 1900; 001116
    - Correspondence. 2 letters. A letter from A.E. Verrill to Office of Tice & Lynch Custom House Brokers protesting the payment of $7.40 for the storage os specimens. A return letter From Tice & Lynch acknowledging the receipt of payment and apologizing for the necessary bill., 20 Oct 1890 - 22 Oct 1890; 001103
  - Exchanges. Archives related to Divisional exchanges., 1864-Present; 001101
    - Exchanges. 2 lists of spiders, one list to be sent to J.H. Emerton and one to be sent to William Holden., 02 Jul 1874 - 18 Sep 1874; 001360
    - Exchanges. A list of Mollusca sent to P.P. Carpenter, some to be retained by Carpenter. Probably in exchange. See Invoice Ledger., 13 Mar 1868; 001406
    - Exchanges. List of Lithobiidae (centipedes) sent to Anton Stuxberg. The genera include Lithobius and Bothropolys., 15 Mar 1875; 001343
    - Exchanges. A list of Mollusca possibly related to an exchange with C.F. Lutken. See Invoice Ledger., 1865; 001397
    - Exchanges. A list of brids and bird eggs received in exchange from the Chicago Academy of Sciences. Some of the specimens originated at the USNM. See Invoice Ledger, 1865; 001471
    - Exchanges. A list of the Duplicates of American Echinoderms in Yale College Museum. Within the folded list is a list of Echinodermata for C.F. Lutken., 1866-1926; 001203
    - Exchanges. A list of Insects sent to the Essex Institute. Some in exchange., 1866; 001198
    - Exchanges. List of sspecimens sent to C.C. Nutting in exchange. Mostly Hydrozoa., 1895-1896; 001102
    - Exchanges. A list of spiders sent to William Holden, presumably in exchange., 21 Apr 1874; 001359
    - Exchanges. A list of Mollusca sent to P.P. Carpenter for identification. Some were to be retained by Carpenter, probably in exchange. See Invoice Ledger., 24 Dec 1867; 001405
    - Exchanges. A letter from the Smithsonian Institute acknowledging the receipt of 5 specimens, Pocillopora frendosa, Pocillopora nobilis var. tuberosa, Coenopsammia tenuilamellosa, Montipora patula and Porites languinosa, in exchange. USNM Acc. No. 44293., 25 May 1905; 001108
    - Exchanges. List of Echinodermata from the Essex Institute. Some were to be returned to the Essex Instutue. See Invoice Ledger., 27 Nov 1866; 001461
    - Exchanges. A list of Specimens received from the Boston Society of Natural History in exchange. Mostly Cnidaria and Echinodermata. See Invoice Ledger., Apr 1867; 001425
    - Exchanges. A list of specimens requested from the Museum of Comparative Zoology by A.E. Verrill for Yale College. Appear to be all Anthozoa., Apr 1868; 001200
    - Exchanges. A list of Annulata from C.F. Lutken sent to the Museum in exchange., Apr 1881; 001342
    - Exchanges. A list of specimens (Anthozoa, Echinodermata) from the Essex Institute, most likely in exchange. Specimens have both and Essex Institute and YPM number. See Invoice Ledger., Dec 1866; 001398
    - Exchanges. A Catalog of Fossils sent to Mr. John Cummings, Jr., Jul 1866; 001197
    - Exchanges. A List of Duplicate Alyconaria in the Museum of Yale College which may be sold. A note at the top of the list in Verrill's hand reads "March 1869. Sent to British Museum.", Mar 1869; 001175
    - Exchanges. VarioList of specimens sent to the USNM, most likely in exchange. Most appear to be Crustacea from Bermuda and Brazil., Mar 1901; 001723
    - Exchanges. A list of of specimens sent to the Boston Society of Natural History. Mostly Echinodermata and Anthozoa., May 1865 - Apr 1866; 001199
    - Exchanges. A list of Invertebrata sent to Prof. Sanborn Tenney of Vassas College. Unsure if it was in exchange. See Invoice Ledger., 001393
    - Exchanges. A list of Corals (Anthozoa) from the MCZ. Most likely in exchange. See Invoice Ledger., 001404
    - Exchanges. Various lists of specimens from, and sent to the USNM., 001706
    - Exchanges. List of specimens sent in exchange with the Brooklyn Institute. Includes Pycnogonida and Annelida., 001856
  - Ledgers. Ledgers detailing divisional loans, exchanges and aquisitions., 1864-Present; 001084
    - Ledgers. Divisional Invoice Ledger. Compilation of lists, correspondence, etc. detailing Division of Zoology aquisitions of collections and donations from various researchers and institutions. Includes lists of invertebrates, insects, birds, etc., 1864-1906; 001088
    - Ledgers. The Divisional Loans and Exchanges ledger., Nov 1865 - Nov 1949; 001086
    - Ledgers. A small ledger labeled as "Memoranda of Donations" listing some donations from Sep 1872 to 1873., Sep 1872 - 1873; 001085
  - Loans. Archives related to divisonal loans., 1866 - Present; 001332
    - Loans. Lit of fishes sent to the USNM for identification by David Starr Jordan. Duplicates were to be retained by the USNM and a series for Jordan. There is what appears to be a corresponding list of the specimens sent back to the Peabody Museum., 24 Oct 1882; 001333
    - Loans. A list of butterflies sent to S.H. Scudder on loan. A note on the list by S.H. Scudder informs of their return and the possibility of an exchange. See Invoice Ledger., Feb 1868; 001417
- Divisional Correspondence, 1866-2011; Series VI
  Correspondence related to various divisional activities.
  - D.S. Sheldon Correspondence. Correspondence from D.S. Sheldon, Griswold College, Davenport, Iowa., 1876; 001854
    - D.S. Sheldon Correspondence. A letter from D.S. Sheldon asking for the identification of 6 specimens of Crustacea from Davenport, Iowa. Unknown who the letter was addressed to., 07 Aug 1876; 001855
  - Dorothy Verrill Rhodes Correspondence. Correspondence from Dorothy Verrill Rhodes, A.E. Verrill's grand daughter., 1961; 001126
    - Dorothy Verrill Rhodes Correspondence. A letter and 6 photographs from D.V. Rhodes to W.D. Hartman. The letter is informing Dr. Hartman that she has completed transcribing various letters to A.E. Verrill. The content of the transcribed letters have been cataloged seperately as A.E. Verrill Correspondence. The 6 photographs appear to be of A.E. Verrill, possibly his son George and and unknow woman., 02 Oct 1961; 001127
    - Dorothy Verrill Rhodes Correspondence. A physical copy of D.V. Rhodes transcription of letters to A.E. Verrill from various researchers., 02 Oct 1961; 005710
  - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. Correspondence from H.A. Pilsbry., 1925; 001619
    - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. A letter from H.A. Pilsbry to Charles Schuchert informing Schuchert he is returning all the Beecher material he had borrowed., 19 Nov 1925; 001620
  - Prof. W.A. Parker Correspondence. Correspondence from W.A. Parker., 001465
    - Prof. W.A. Parker Correspondence. A letter from W.A. Parker, apparently forwarded by Prof. D.C. Eaton. In the the letter Parker is concerned about the state of the Yale College Museum and asks if he deposited specimens can he maintain a right of reclaiming in the futre. A note in J.D. Dana's hand reads "improbable." There is a note on the back of the letter in Verrill's hand that lists some species names. Possible related to YPMZ Acc. No. 212. See Invoice Ledger., 001466
  - Robinson Verrill Correspondence. Correspondence from Robinson Verrill., 1962; 001164